Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (6th: 1899) records 1896-1899
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Legislative Assembly (6th: 1899) records
1896-1899
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 6
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
.6 linear feet of shelf space
Records (1896-1899) of the Montana 6th Legislative Assembly consist of minutes and report of Joint Special and House standing committees; and miscellany, including correspondence, petitions, and subject files on contested elections. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1]
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 6th Montana Legislature met from January 2nd to March 2nd, 1899. The leaders of the Senate were Archibald Spriggs (Populist-President), and Thomas Cullen (D-President Pro Tempore). The leaders of the House were Henry Stiff (D-Speaker), and Edwin Lamb (D-Speaker Pro Tempore).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
Records (1896-1899) of the Montana 6th Legislative Assembly consist of minutes and report of Joint Special Committee to Investigate Matters of Bribery Connected with Senatorial Elections (re William A. Clark); minutes of House standing committees; and miscellany, including correspondence, petitions (re support of Sunday closure of businesses; support of the establishment of Rosebud County; opposing changes in Madison County boundaries; supporting creation of a new state judicial district consisting of Ravalli and Granite Counties; opposing repeal of anti-gambling law; support of direct legislation; support of reclamation of state lands; exemption of grocers from liquor tax; support of legislation favoring union typographers; supporting fish screen on natural streams for irrigation; supporting repeal of the bounty law on wild animals; supporting increase in the bounty on grey wolves; supporting legislation shortening hunting season on certain game birds; supporting the practice of osteopaths; supporting legislation Prohibiting stealing railways rides and trespassing upon freight and passenger trains; and supporting license tax upon traveling salesmen), and subject files on contested elections. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1]
The collection is organized into six series, House and Senate Special Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), House of Representatives Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically), General Correspondence (arranged alphabetically), Subject Files (arranged alphabetically), and Miscellany (arranged alphabetically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Montana--Committees.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana.; Government and Politics.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House and Senate Special Joint Committee Minutes
  - Joint Select Committee to Investigate Matters of Bribery Connected with Senatorial Elections (re W.A. Clark; testimony and report), 1899 January 11-12 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Joint Select Committee on Resolutions (draft resolution re montana regiment serving in Philippine Islands), 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- House of Representatives Standing Committee Minutes
  - Unidentified Committee Actions on Unidentified Bill, 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
- Senate Resolutions
  - Joint Senate Resolution No. 3 [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1], 1899 (Oversizebox OVFD)
- General Correspondence
  - "Message of Hon. Robert B. Smith, Governor of Montana, to the Sixth Legislative Assembly of the State of Montana", 1899 January (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - To the Senate, 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Subject Files
  - Contested Elections: John H. Geiger vs. Fred Whiteside (re Flathead County Senate Seat) [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: Box #1], 1898-1899 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
- Miscellany
  - Board of Examiners (re claim of George D. Garnard and Co. for Standards of Weight and Measures), 1896-1899 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Certification of John W. Ponsford as Sergeant at arms of the Senate, 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - List of State Senators and Representatives by County, 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Petitions (re support of Sunday closure of businesses), 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Petitions (re support of Sunday closure of businesses), 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Petitions (re support of the establishment of Rosebud County; opposing changes in Madison County boundaries; supporting creation of a new state judicial district consisting of Ravalli and Granite Counties), 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Petitions (re opposing repeal of anti-gambling law), 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Petitions (re support of direct legislation), 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Petitions (re support of reclamation of state lands; exemption of grocers from liquor tax; support of legislation favoring union typographers; supporting fish screen on natural streams for irrigation; supporting repeal of the bounty law on wild animals; supporting increase in the bounty on grey wolves; supporting legislation shortening hunting season on certain game birds; supporting the practice of osteopaths; supporting legislation Prohibiting stealing railways rides and trespassing upon freight and passenger trains; and supporting license tax upon traveling salesmen), 1899 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Receipt from State Treasure for Currency used in Evidence by the Joint Committee to Investigate Matters of Bribery in Senatorial Election, 1899 January 10 (Box-folder 1 / 16)